<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preached by Brune Ryves.</title>
            <author>Ryves, Bruno, 1596-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09602488</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09602488</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58044)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1339:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preached by Brune Ryves.</title>
                  <author>Ryves, Bruno, 1596-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"St. Luke 12, 15. Take heed and beware of covetousnesse."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Avarice --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43794:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43794:1"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS, PREACHED BY <hi>BR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NE RYVES,</hi> D. D. AND D. of <hi>C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> LUKE 12. 15.</bibl>
               <p>Take heed and beware of Covetouſneſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:43794:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43794:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 TIM. 6. 10.</bibl>
                  <p>For the Love of money is the Roote of all Evil.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Peter,</hi> ſpeaking of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſayes, <hi>that there are in them, ſome Things hard to be underſtood, 2 Pet.</hi> 3. 16. Though my Text be not to be found, in the Catalogue and Number of thoſe things, which are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>hard to be underſtood,</hi> yet experience tels us, that it is to be found in the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, and number of thoſe things, which are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hard to be believed, for while S. <hi>Paul</hi> before us, and we, after him, preach, that <hi>the Love of Money is the Root of all Evil,</hi> yet the ſmall eredit, that this Apoſtolical, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, finds with the children of this world, gives us too juſt cauſe, to take up that complaint, which our Apoſtle borrows, from the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to this particular, <hi>Lord who hath believed our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</hi> Rom. 10. 16. While therefore I endeavour, to evidence this Truth, to the Conſcience of every man, I ſhall obſerve this method.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I ſhall open the Nature of this Sin, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, This <hi>Love of Money is.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43794:3"/>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall make it appear, to be, as the Apoſtle here Characterizeth it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>The Root of all Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In the Laſt place, for Application. I ſhall offer unto you, Firſt, ſome <hi>motives</hi> to <hi>dehort,</hi> and Secondly, ſome <hi>helps</hi> to <hi>preſerve</hi> you, from ſo dangerous, ſo deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive a Sin.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I muſt ſhew you what this <hi>Love of Money,</hi> is:<note place="margin">Part. 1.</note> Two words there are, in the new Teſtament that uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſerve to expreſſe the Nature of this Sin, the firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, uſually Tranſlated Covetouſneſſe, uſed by S. <hi>Luke, Take heed and beware of Covetouſneſſe,</hi> Luke 12. 15. The Second is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, here uſed by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and tranſlated, <hi>the Love of Money:</hi> From this double ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, <hi>Aquinas</hi> obſerves, that Covetouſneſſe is a<note place="margin">2. 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>. q. 118.</note> Compound, complicate ſin, oppoſed to a double ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the <hi>Rapacious</hi> part of Covetouſneſſe, oppoſed to <hi>Juſtice:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the <hi>Tenacious</hi> part of Covetouſneſſe, oppoſed to <hi>Liberality:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe in <hi>getting,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is Covetouſneſſe in <hi>Keeping:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath a <hi>Large paw,</hi> to get, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more then enough, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is the <hi>Mortmaine</hi> of Covetouſneſſe to detain, and hold back, whatſoever the other hath gotten.</p>
            <p>But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here uſed, and Tranſlated, <hi>The Love of Money,</hi> is not to be bounded within ſo narrow a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, as to ſignifie, but that part only of Covetouſneſs, which is oppoſed to <hi>Liberality,</hi> for as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word <hi>Avaritia</hi> ſayes, <hi>Nomen Avaritiae am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliandum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. Art 2.</note> 
               <hi>eſt,</hi> The word Covetouſneſſe is to be extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a general ſignification of every inordinate deſire, of having any thing: And as S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in his book <hi>De
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43794:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Doctrinâ Chriſtianâ,</hi> inlargeth the word <hi>Money,</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, not only <hi>Menſuram Valoris Rerum,</hi> the meaſure of the value of things but the very things themſelves, <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſunt domini, pecunia vocantur,</hi> whatſoever we are owners of, may be called our money; for ſo God ſayes of a hired Servant, <hi>Pecunia tua eſt, he is thy money, Ex.</hi> 21. 21. So the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, here, <hi>Nomen amplian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt,</hi> is not to be ſhrunk up to the narrow circle, of whoſe Image and Superſcription is this, to ſignifie Coyn only, but to be enlarged ſo far, as to comprehend under its Latitude, the vaſt, and boundleſſe extent, both of the deſires, endeavours, and ſinfull acts, of the ſin of Covetouſneſſe: And therefore S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> and the whole ſtream of the Latin Fathers, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here, by <hi>Avaritia,</hi> the common word, whereby they render both <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: And though <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and after him the Schools, have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note place="margin">2. 2<hi rend="sup">ae</hi>. q. 113. Art. 4.</note> an eaſie cenſure on this <hi>Love of Money,</hi> and (unleſs upon ſuppoſition of Imperfection of the Act, or Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from Charity) have blanched it into a <hi>Venial ſin,</hi> yet S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who beſt knew the nature of this ſin, points out the malignity of it, in a truer Character, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Love of Money is the Root of all Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is no leſſe, then, <hi>Injuſta Acquiſitio</hi> and <hi>Illegitima detentio,</hi> unjuſt getting of wealth and unlawful keeping of it; It is <hi>Amor nimius, &amp; Amor nimii,</hi> A deſire, inflamed, more then enough, of having more then enovgh: In a word, it is no other, then the Adequate ſubject of S. <hi>Auguſtins</hi> Definition of Covetouſneſſe, who ſayes, that it is, <hi>Plus velle quàm fateſt,</hi> an Inordinate deſire of having, and keeping
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43794:4"/>
more wealth, then, what is enough. <hi>Lib. 3. De Lib. Arb. cap.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>In which Definition, <hi>two</hi> things need Explanation, <hi>Firſt,</hi> what that is, that makes the deſire of wealth to be <hi>Inordinate? Secondly,</hi> how we ſhall know what is <hi>Enough?</hi> what bounds, and limits we ſhall ſet unto it? ſince it is evident, that it doth not conſiſt <hi>In Puncto In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſibili,</hi> in any one particular meaſure, or proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whatſoever.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Firſt,</hi> divers things there are, that render the deſire of wealth to be <hi>Inordinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> a wrong <hi>Method,</hi> when we ſeek wealth <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterouſly,</hi> when that which ſhould be <hi>firſt,</hi> is the <hi>laſt</hi> thing in our endeavours: when (contrary to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Precept <hi>Seek ye firſt the kingdom of God and his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Righteouſneſs, &amp;c.</hi>) we ſuffer, this <hi>Love of Money,</hi> to take up, if not the whole, yet the Principal, and firſt place in our endeavours, and affections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> when, <hi>the Love of Money,</hi> doth rule, not only in our <hi>affections,</hi> but in our <hi>judgements</hi> too, ſo, that we eſteem it far above its true value, and more then its worth can merit: when, we magnifie wealth ſo far, as to account all men happy, that have it, and our ſelves, and all others miſerable that want it. Hence proceed diſcontent at our preſent eſtate, murmuring, and repining, at Gods Providence, for denying us ſuch a meaſure of the Riches of this world, expoſtulating, as for an Injury, why did not God make me Rich? and not onely ſo, but hence ſprings envey at another mans proſperity, and plenty, an evil eye at our neighbours wealth, and a ſetled reſolution to be rich, <hi>Per fas &amp; nefas,</hi> to the loſſe, not onely of <hi>quietneſſe,</hi> and <hi>content,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:43794:4"/>
but of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> alſo; according to that of <hi>Solomon, He that makes haſte to be Rich, ſhall not be Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> Prov. 28. 20. and that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> here, <hi>They that will be rich,</hi> (that is, that are reſolved to be ſo) <hi>fall into Temptation and a ſnare,</hi> at the verſe before my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> when that reliance, that truſt, and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which is due to <hi>God,</hi> is placed in <hi>Riches,</hi> when we do <hi>Cor apponere, ſet our hearts upon them,</hi> Pſal. 62. 10. and make them our refuge, when, inſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God our portion, and our inheritance, we do, as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Make gold our hope, and ſay unto the fine gold thou art my confidence,</hi> Job 31. 24. upon this very ground S. <hi>Paul</hi> cals Covetouſneſſe, <hi>Idolatry,</hi> Col. 3. 5. and the covetous man, an <hi>Idolater,</hi> Eph. 5. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> when we are over hot in the proſecution of wealth, and ſo eager, as neither to ſtay Gods leiſure, no, nor ſo much as to take his directions along with us in getting it: when we endeavour to get wealth, with diſtracted carefulneſſe, and anxiety, <hi>making</hi> (as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>our dayes ſorrow, our travel grief, and our hearts to take no reſt in the night,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> when we ſet no bounds, no limits to our appetite, when we enlarge our deſires, as hell, to lade our ſelves with thick clay, and ſuffer thoſe deſires, to increaſe, with our wealth, the ſoul, by a reſtleſſe ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, ſtill fighting againſt its own ſatisfaction, by deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring more: In this, coming ſhort of the moderation, even of profane <hi>Eſau,</hi> who refuſed his Brother <hi>Jacobs</hi> preſents, with an <hi>Abunde mihi ſatis eſt, mi Frater, I have enough my Brother,</hi> Gen. 33. 9. which points, at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing in this Definition, needing Explanation, <hi>viz.</hi> How we ſhall know, what this <hi>enough</hi> is, ſince it is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43794:5"/>
evident, that it doth not conſiſt <hi>In Puncto indiviſibili,</hi> in any one particular, preſcribed, or limited proportion, or meaſure, whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Two</hi> wayes there are to find out this Proportion, <hi>Firſt,</hi> by thoſe <hi>lawful means,</hi> which God affords for the Moderate getting of wealth: and <hi>Secondly</hi> by our <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt way to know what this <hi>Enough</hi> is, is, by thoſe <hi>lawful means,</hi> which God gives for the getting of wealth: God, in his divine providence, hath not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded to all men, an equal proportion of theſe means, &amp; therefore it is evident, that in the diſpenſations of his Providence, he did not intend, an equal proportion of wealth to all: for God is no <hi>Leveller,</hi> but a God of <hi>Order:</hi> So that as in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Viſion, the motion of the <hi>wheels,</hi> was anſwerable to the motion of the <hi>creatures,</hi> when <hi>theſe</hi> went, <hi>thoſe</hi> went, when <hi>theſe</hi> ſtood ſtill, the <hi>other</hi> did not move, and the Reaſon of this Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, was, becauſe <hi>the Spirit of the Living Creatures was in the wheels,</hi> Ezek. 1. 20. So in this caſe, the <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of our <hi>wealth</hi> muſt be proportioned, to the <hi>means,</hi> which God affords us for the getting of wealth, when theſe move, and are enlarged, our deſires may move with them, when theſe ſtand ſtill, and reſt, ſo muſt our deſires. And the Reaſon, why they muſt move, and reſt together, is, becauſe the proportion of Gods allotment, is in the means, as the ſpirit of the creatures was in the wheels: ſo that if God cut ſhort the <hi>means,</hi> to get wealth, we muſt contract our <hi>deſires,</hi> and cauſe them to move in an equipage anſwerable, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate to them, <hi>Small means</hi> to <hi>get wealth,</hi> and <hi>ſmall deſires</hi> of <hi>having wealth,</hi> ſuit beſt together.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43794:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> as this proportion of our wealth may be known, by the <hi>means,</hi> which God affords us for the getting of wealth; So it is known, by our <hi>Neceſſities,</hi> Now there is a Fourfold <hi>Neceſſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> there is <hi>Neceſſitas Naturae,</hi> the <hi>Neceſſity of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> which is the Proportion ſo rigidly preſcribed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> but not ſo ſtrictly practized by them: <hi>Natura paucis contenta,</hi> ſayes <hi>Seneca, Nature is content with a little:</hi> If you aſk her for a <hi>bill of fare,</hi> ſhe writes <hi>bread, and water,</hi> if you would have Nature, to furniſh a <hi>Wardrobe,</hi> ſhe provides, <hi>Lodging and Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to cover our Nakedneſs,</hi> Eccleſ. 39. 16. 'Tis true, what is her due, ſhe will not be denied, for, <hi>Contumax eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 119.</note> 
               <hi>ſuum poſcit,</hi> ſayes the ſame <hi>Stoick,</hi> ſhe is a rigid exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, and claims her due, but yet ſhe is not chargeable, for, <hi>Qui ſe ad id quod Natura exigit, compoſuit, non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>extra ſenſum paupertatis eſt, ſed extra metum:</hi> as the ſame <hi>Philoſopher ſpeaks, He that bounds himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Exigencies of Nature, is out of the danger, not only of the ſenſe, and feeling of poverty, but of the fear alſo:</hi> But Religion doth not confine us to ſo narrow a compaſſe, ſo ſtreight a Sphere, as the neceſſity of Nature: yet if occaſion ſerve, our Apoſtle in this Chapter, gives a precept looking this way, <hi>Habentes victum &amp; veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c. having food, and raiment, let us therewith be content,</hi> verſe 8. for <hi>theſe,</hi> in S. <hi>Jeroms</hi> account, are no leſſe, then, <hi>Divitiae Chriſtianorum, The Riches of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> Nay long before Chriſtianity, taught the world this moderation, <hi>Jacob</hi> articled with God for no more, but <hi>Protection, food, and raiment: If God will be with me, and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me bread to eat, and rayment to put on, &amp;c. then ſhall the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43794:6"/>
Lord be my God,</hi> Geneſis 28. 20, 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> there is <hi>Neceſſitas Perſonae,</hi> a Neceſſity of a mans particular <hi>Perſon,</hi> to maintain our bodies, in Strength, and cheerfulneſſe; for the better inabling us, in the diſcharge of our general, and particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: And this doth vary, according to the diverſities of mens <hi>Education, Temperature,</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and the like; One man, with <hi>Jacob,</hi> being able to endure the heat of the day, and the froſt of the night; to riſe up early, and late take reſt, and to eat the bread of carefulneſſe, and yet with <hi>Daniel</hi> and his companions, proſper better with their courſe fare, then the reſt which had their Portions from the Kings table. One, is able to quench his thirſt with <hi>water,</hi> and with <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſouldiers, to lap it out of the next brook, when ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is fain, to make uſe of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> preſcription to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy, Drink no longer water, but uſe a little wine, for thy ſtomacks ſake, and thine often infirmities,</hi> Chap. 5. of this Epiſt. verſe 23.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there is <hi>Neceſſitas Expedientiae,</hi> a Neceſſity (as I may ſo call it) of <hi>Expediencie:</hi> when, beſides things <hi>neceſſary,</hi> there is ſome regard to be had to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency,</hi> when beſides, what is abſolutely neceſſary to our <hi>Subſiſtance,</hi> there is ſomething indulged to our <hi>Refreſhment:</hi> and therefore it was but way wardly done of the <hi>Cynick,</hi> to caſt away his <hi>diſh,</hi> as ſuperfluous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſaw a boy, drink water out of the <hi>hollow of his hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, there is <hi>Neceſſitas Conditionis,</hi> a Neceſſity of our Calling and Condition of life; which admits a very great Latitude, according to the various Relations, and Stations, which men hold, both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43794:6"/>
ſo that, that, which is but <hi>neceſſary,</hi> for a maſter of a Family, may be ſuperfluous to him, that is not burdened with thoſe Relations, and Dependencies: That which is but <hi>enough</hi> for a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> whoſe port, and condition, needs greater ſupplies, may be <hi>too much</hi> for a <hi>private man,</hi> who needs not thoſe poor, but yet neceſſary advantages, to commend him to the awe, and diſtance of the vulgar. Laſtly, that which is but neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for a Miniſter, in reſpect of thoſe duties which God requires of him, as, <hi>Hoſpitality,</hi> Chap. 3. of this Epiſtle, verſe 2. <hi>Attendance upon the Altar, attendance upon preaching,</hi> and neglecting all other means of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, attendance upon <hi>ſtudy, and reading,</hi> Cha. 4. of this Epiſtle, verſe 6. <hi>Caeteris paribus,</hi> may be too much for a man, not abſtracted, and ſequeſtred, from the world, not conſecrated, and ſet apart, for thoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Imployments.</p>
            <p>And as this is true of our preſent Neceſſities, ſo we may judge of this <hi>Enough,</hi> by our <hi>future neceſſities,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of S. <hi>Paul, The children ought not to lay up for the Parents, but the Parents for the children,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 14. And, <hi>if any man provide not for his own, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for thoſe of his own houſhold, he hath denied the faith, and is worſe then an Infidel,</hi> Chap. 5. of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, verſe 8. both which places, look beyond the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, and do injoyn, not only a moderate care for the preſent, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, though not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a lawful providence, though not a diſtruſtful, anxious careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for the time to come.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly ſhewed you, what this <hi>love of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> is in it ſelf, and in its own Nature, I come now to ſhew, what it is in its effects, and ſo it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Root of all Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43794:7"/>And here to a people trained up in Chriſtianity, it<note place="margin">Part. 2.</note> may ſeem ſuperfluous, to go about to prove, that this <hi>Love of Money</hi> is a Sin, or at leaſt a Sin, ſo exceeding ſinful as to be a teeming, mother ſin, <hi>The Root of all Evil;</hi> but upon a ſtrict ſurvey, we ſhall find it, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not ſuperfluous, but very neceſſary, for while other ſins are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelf-condemning, ſelf-convicting ſins, Infamous in their very ſurface, and outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, as carrying their own <hi>Stigma,</hi> and brand in their foreheads, <hi>The love of Money,</hi> is a ſin no leſſe, nay, perhaps more ſinful then the reſt, &amp; yet, is uſually paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over, with leſſe obſervation, hardly with any note of Infamy caſt upon it, as if the object of it were not the <hi>Mammon of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> and it ſelf, <hi>The Root of all Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet not, that we are ſo to underſtand S. <hi>Paul,</hi> as if every particular ſin, committed by the children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, did owe its being, and guilt, to this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; No, the word <hi>All,</hi> here, is not <hi>collective,</hi> but <hi>diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and to be taken, not, <hi>Pro Singulis Generum,</hi> but <hi>Pro Generibus Singulorum:</hi> And that, becauſe, <hi>Firſt,</hi> it gives life, and being to ſome ſins of all kinds; or, <hi>Secondly,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as it breeds many ſins, ſo it foments, and nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth more; <hi>Thirdly,</hi> becauſe it diſpoſeth the Perſon in whom it reigns, to the perpetration of any ſin, that may conduce to the ſatisfaction of its <hi>canine appetite,</hi> for <hi>cui nihil ſatis, Nihil turpe,</hi> He that thinks nothing <hi>Enough,</hi> will never boggle at any thing, or ſcruple it, as wicked, and ſinful; or <hi>Laſtly,</hi> the Apoſtle may in a juſt deteſtation of this ſin, call it <hi>the root of all evil,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the Root not only of that evil, which the Schools call <hi>Malum Culpae,</hi> the evil of guilt, but of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43794:7"/>
other evil alſo, which they call <hi>Malum Poenae,</hi> the evil of Puniſhment: I ſhall inſiſt on both, and ſhew it to be, Firſt, The <hi>Root, of the evil of guilt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here, it is not my intent with <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and the School-men, to preſent you with a long Catalogue, or large Pedegree of the numerous off-ſpring of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy mother, or point at every branch of this impure Root; I ſhall not ſtand to ſhew you, what ſway it bears, what influence it hath, on moſt of the Actions of men; How it ſteals into the <hi>Juntoes</hi> of States, votes in the <hi>grand Counſels</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and mingles in the conſultations, and deliberations of Kingdoms, Nations, and Common-wealths, and over-rules their Reſults, to particular advantages: I ſhall not now ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign it for perverting of Judgement, and Juſtice, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing power, and authority, to oppreſſion, and wrong: making both <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to ſtoop, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, with its <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>commands:</hi> I ſhall not now tell you, how it <hi>pants after the duſt of the Earth, on the head of the poor,</hi> Amos 2. 7. what ſpoil it makes in the Country, how it depopulates in one Lordſhip, and racks the Tenants in an other, In both perhaps, robbing the Labourer of his hire, and grinding the faces of the poor: I ſhall not lead you through the ſtreets of your own City, and taking down the dark cloth, ſhew you, where it ſtands at the tradeſmans elbow, and brok's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>buyer,</hi> and the <hi>ſeller;</hi> how it teacheth one to <hi>ingroſſe</hi> Commodities, and another to <hi>adulterate</hi> them: In a word, I ſhall not now ſtand to tell you, how this one ſin, hath filled both Country, and City, <hi>with Men as with Caterpillers,</hi> as God threatned <hi>Babylon,</hi> Jer. 51. 14. Nor ſhall I aggravate its ſinfulneſſe, by ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43794:8"/>
that it made, <hi>Achan</hi> undergo the curſe of <hi>God the Father,</hi> Tempted <hi>Judas,</hi> to betray <hi>God the Son,</hi> betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> to <hi>lye unto the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> nor Laſtly, ſhall I demonſtrate unto you, how incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, and directly oppoſite it is, to the <hi>three Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal vertues, Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> No! ſome <hi>ſower fruits</hi> there are, that ſpring from this <hi>root,</hi> more appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to theſe unhappy times, and have ſet our teeth on edge, and of <hi>theſe,</hi> I ſhall name but ſome.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Averſion from,</hi> and, <hi>Indiſpoſition to piety</hi> and devotion, Alienation of the affections from God, and his ſervice, all ſpring from this <hi>Root:</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> accuſeth the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to God, for diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to, and neglect of, the word, preached by him, but withall, gives the Reaſon, points out the Thief, that had ſtoln away their hearts from God, <hi>They will not do thy words, for their heart goeth after their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe,</hi> Ezek. 33. 31. This made <hi>David</hi> to pray ſo earneſtly againſt this Sin, <hi>Incline my heart, O Lord, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Teſtimonies, and not unto covetouſneſſe,</hi> Pſal. 119. 36. where the <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> or <hi>Oppoſition</hi> which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet makes, between, <hi>inclining his heart to Gods Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> and, <hi>not unto Covetouſneſs,</hi> is very remarkable, <hi>Incline my heart unto thy Teſtimonies, and not unto Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs,</hi> where, <hi>Not unto Covetouſneſs,</hi> ſhews, that theſe <hi>two,</hi> are Incompatible, and cannot poſſibly conſiſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, A <hi>Heart,</hi> ſet, on <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> and at the ſame time ſet, on <hi>Gods commandments: Nemo poteſt amplecti, Dei gratiam, ſimul, &amp; Seculi,</hi> ſayes S. <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> And yet, behold a greater then S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is here, and bears Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to this Truth, <hi>Ye cannot ſerve God, and Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 24. This ſin, of all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43794:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
others, doth, as it were, Tranſubſtantiate the ſoul, from <hi>Spirit,</hi> to <hi>Earth:</hi> If the Covetous, chance to read the Bible, he magnifies the <hi>promiſes</hi> of the <hi>Old</hi> Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment far above thoſe of the <hi>New, Theſe,</hi> being but <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> of certain Notional things, which ſilly Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, call <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> Things which he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not: The <hi>other,</hi> are of things <hi>Temporal,</hi> obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to ſight, as long life, and plenty, A Land flowing with milk, and honey, Garners, full, and plenteous with all manner of ſtore; Sheep, bringing forth Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and ten thouſands in our ſtreets: If he think on the <hi>Temporal Jeruſalem,</hi> he is much pleaſed with it, conſidered as it was in <hi>Solomons</hi> reign, <hi>who made ſilver to be in Jeruſalem, as ſtones for abundance,</hi> 1 Kings 10. 27. If he chance to meditate, on the <hi>heavenly Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> he is raviſhed with the deſcription of it, and, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of reaſon, reſolves, not to admit of an <hi>Allegory,</hi> when he reads, <hi>Her gates are of pearl, and her ſtreets of pure gold,</hi> Revel. 21. 21. He doth not ſo much magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie S. <hi>Paul,</hi> for his Rapture, into the third heaven, as, he doth contemn S. <hi>Peter,</hi> for profeſſing his poverty, <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and gold have I none,</hi> Acts 3. 6. If he <hi>wake,</hi> all the Inferiour Globe rowls in his brains: There ſail the ſhips, aye, and there graſe the ſheep, and cattel upon a Thouſand hils: There, are Hedges, and Ditches,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 10.</note> Cloſes, Towns, and Tenements, Markets, and Faires, Purchaſes, and Mortgages, Leaſes, Bils, and Bonds: If he <hi>ſleep,</hi> he doth not ſo much as dream of Heaven, his habit of Covetouſneſſe, makes his very ſlumbers ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: A perfect Son of the <hi>old Adam, who was from the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 47.</note> 
               <hi>Earth earthly:</hi> certainly God is not in all his thoughts: And therefore, as God is not in his <hi>Love,</hi> ſo, he is in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43794:9"/>
Gods <hi>hatred: The Covetous whom God abhorreth,</hi> Pſal. 10. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> ſpring from this root; 'Tis evident in <hi>Judas, Judas</hi> was <hi>Covetous,</hi> and a <hi>Traytor,,</hi> and therefore a Traytor, becauſe Covetous, He did not only <hi>carry,</hi> but <hi>love</hi> the <hi>bagge:</hi> He ſold his Maſter, not out of <hi>hatred</hi> to his <hi>Maſters Perſon,</hi> but out of <hi>love</hi> to the <hi>thirty pieces of ſilver:</hi> The wages of unrighteouſneſſe hath ſeduced more beſides <hi>Balaam:</hi> And therefore when <hi>Sextius</hi> and <hi>Licinius,</hi> Two ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tribunes of the People, had uſurped, all power, over the people, and Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the ſpace of<note place="margin">Liv. l. 6.</note> nine years; and reigned in the City, <hi>Tanquam, Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, ac Tacius, Appius Claudius,</hi> in his Oration, againſt thoſe Rebels, obſerves, that, as <hi>Covetouſneſſe</hi> was the firſt Incentive, to theſe <hi>Seditions,</hi> to begin their <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſo, <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> was that, which did foment, and ſpin it out to that length: for all this was: <hi>Quia pecuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as alienas, quia agros, dono dant tanta dulcedo eſt ex alienis fortunis praedandi,</hi> as he there ſpeaks: <hi>by an uſurped power, they invaded, and gave away other mens moneys, and other mens poſſeſſions, ſo ſweet a thing it is, to grow rich by Rapine, and Oppreſſion, and to make other mens for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, the prey of Treaſon and Rebellion:</hi> But it is a tender Argument, and I ſhall proſecute it no further.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> from this Root ſprings <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> that abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, of deſolation, in the Church of God: <hi>Will a man rob God?</hi> ſayes the Prophet, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 8. Why? can God be robbed? There are I confeſſe, a Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men, that do not only <hi>Sceptically</hi> move the doubt, but <hi>Dogmatically,</hi> though <hi>Atheiſtically,</hi> reſolve for the Negative, As if God, when he gave us his Son,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43794:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
had, with him, ſo freely given us all things, as if he <hi>could not,</hi> or at leaſt, <hi>would not,</hi> accept of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, of our thankful Homage, and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his dominion, over all the works of his hands, by an Oblation, of a <hi>holy Portion,</hi> Ezek. 45. 1. Theſe are the Righteous (as they pretend) that ſhould <hi>poſſeſſe the Earth;</hi> aye, ſo poſſeſſe it, that God himſelf, ſhall have no portion, no ſhare in the <hi>Divident:</hi> But certainly, God hath loſt, neither his <hi>Dominion</hi> over the whole, nor his <hi>Propertie</hi> in any portion, that piety, or devotion, ſhall conſecrate unto him: The Prophet therefore, makes no doubt of the poſſibility, but that a man may rob God, except it be of a Moral poſſibilitie, <hi>Will a man rob God?</hi> That is, can any man be ſo deſperately wicked, ſo much the child of the Devil, and not the Devil himſelf, as to rob God? his own God? ſome bold <hi>Sacrilegi</hi> there have been, that have adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to rob the Gods of other Nations, yet, <hi>In Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Religione nil tale ſine vindicta,</hi> as <hi>Lactantius</hi> truly obſerves, <hi>never without due puniſhment following upon ſuch Sacriledge,</hi> as if God, the puniſhment of Sacriledge, committed on the <hi>Anathemata,</hi> Gifts, conſecrated to <hi>falſe Gods,</hi> ſhould, as by a kind of <hi>Pedagogie,</hi> teach his own, to keep clean hands, from whatever was dedicated to the <hi>True:</hi> He that doubts of this, let him but read, that Oration, of the <hi>Locri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liv. l. 29.</note> in <hi>Livy,</hi> concerning the ſpoil done, Firſt by <hi>Pyrrus,</hi> and afterward, by the Roman Garriſon, on the Temple, and treaſury, of their Goddeſſe <hi>Proſerpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na:</hi> But yet, can any man arive at that height of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43794:10"/>
Impiety, as to rob <hi>his own God?</hi> or if one ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious monſter may poſſibly be found, amongſt men, yet ſhall we find ſuch a People? will a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rob God? their own God? yes, <hi>the Love of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> can do this too, 'Tis the root of all Evil, This great Evil, <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> Robbing of God, Robbing our own God: But what will follow? why, that which follows in the Prophet, <hi>Mal. 3. 9. Maledicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Maledicti eſtis, Ye are curſed with a Curſe, for ye have robbed me, even this whole Nation;</hi> and if ye would know, what this <hi>curſe</hi> is, do but read the 83 Pſalm; I do not know, whether there be more <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> or <hi>terrour</hi> in it, at the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> verſe, you ſhall find a crafty councel, or combination of all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Church, to deſtroy the members of the Church, and to invade their poſſeſſions, for the reſult of the councel, is, <hi>Let us take to our ſelves, the houſes of God into poſſeſſion,</hi> verſe 12. But the word, is no ſooner out of their mouths, but the Curſe of God followeth upon the neck of it, <hi>Pone eos ut Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam: O my God make them like a wheel, and as the ſtubble before the wind, like as the fire that burneth up the wood, and as the ſlame that conſumeth the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, ſo perſecute them with thy Tempeſt, &amp; make them afraid with thy ſtorm, let them be confounded, and troubled for ever, yea, let them be put to ſhame, and periſh, &amp;c.</hi> verſe 13, 14, 15, &amp;c. And now, if any man hath a longing, to devour that which is <hi>holy,</hi> to ſwallow up the <hi>Patrimony</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> of his <hi>Spouſe</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> He ſees here, at what rate he may do it: 'Tis a dreadful Curſe: and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43794:10"/>
yet, I am afraid, that there are too many, that have an itch to ſhare in the <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and as for the <hi>Curſe,</hi> to put that to the adventure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> it is the Root of <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> and falling off from God, and that in a double Reſpect, Firſt in reſpect of the <hi>truth it ſelf,</hi> and Secondly, in Reſpect of the <hi>open profeſſion of the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Firſt,</hi> the Apoſtle here is poſitive, <hi>The Love of Money is the Root of all Evil, which while ſome coveted after, they have erred from the faith:</hi> and not onely ſo, They have erred not only in their own perſons, but for gaine, they have turned Huckſters of the word of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the falſe teachers of his time: <hi>Corrupting the word of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 2. 17. As <hi>Hucksters,</hi> that mingle bad, with good, that ſo the good, may countenance, and vent the bad: and through Covetouſneſſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>They ſhall make merchandize of you, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 3. Expoſe their followers to ſale, as wares at a publick Mart: Nay, by this means, they do, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Col. 2. 8. Praedam abigere,</hi> drive away the prey, as when after a victorie, companies of men, herds of cattel, and flocks of ſheep, amaſſed into a body, are driven away, as ſpoils, before the conquerours: Nay, S. <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his third Epiſtle, goes higher, and ſayes, that they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men, that for gain, ſet Chriſt himſelf to ſale: And God knows, too many ſuch merchants, we have, now a dayes, who <hi>teach ſuch things as they ought not, for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucres ſake,</hi> Tit. 1. 11. who, through the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43794:11"/>
and Schiſms which they make, rend the ſeam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe coat of Chriſt, diſturb the common peace of the Church, and <hi>ſerve not the Lord Chriſt, but their own bellies,</hi> Rom. 16. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> as it is the Root of <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Integrity of the Truth,</hi> ſo it is the Root of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy</hi> alſo, in reſpect of the <hi>open profeſſion of that Truth:</hi> 'Tis more then probable, that this, was <hi>Demas</hi> his <hi>Apoſtacy: Demas</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me, having embraced this preſent world,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 10. It ſeemes, he thought it ſafer, to cloſe with the world, or as we uſually call it, <hi>make his peace,</hi> then run the hazard of loſing his eſtate, by adhering to a perſecuted Truth: Our Saviour tels us that there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the deceitfulneſſe of Riches, Mark</hi> 4. 19. And certainly, never age did afford, more, and greater examples of their deceitfulneſſe, then this age of ours: I know not whether <hi>hope of gain</hi> on <hi>one</hi> ſide, or <hi>fear of loſing</hi> on the <hi>other,</hi> hath decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved moſt: Good God, <hi>how hardly ſhall a rich man enter into the kingdom of God?</hi> I am aſhamed to ſpeak it, but I have this to accuſe my nation of, this <hi>Love of Money,</hi> hath ſo poſſeſſed their hearts, that they meaſure, not only <hi>honeſty,</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> but <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf by gain: Nay, 'tis much to be feared, that if ſome might enjoy their own in peace, they would not only ſubmit to <hi>Schiſms,</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> but embrace the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and ſubmit to <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme,</hi> if they were propoſed, as a condition.</p>
            <p>And now this <hi>Love of Money,</hi> being ſo fertile a mother, of the <hi>Evil of guilt,</hi> you cannot imagin, it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43794:11"/>
ſhould be barren, of the <hi>Evil of Puniſhment:</hi> God therefore, to the covetous mans <hi>Malum Culpae,</hi> adds, his <hi>Malum Poenae,</hi> For God doth uſually puniſh ſuch a ſinner; <hi>Firſt,</hi> in his <hi>Eſtate, Secondly,</hi> in his <hi>Children,</hi> and <hi>Poſterity,</hi> and <hi>Laſtly</hi> in his <hi>own Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> God doth puniſh him in his <hi>Eſtate,</hi> and that, <hi>Firſt,</hi> by <hi>giving him wealth, but denying him a heart to uſe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> by bereaving him of his Idol, which he adored, and depriving him, of that wealth, on which he ſo much doted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> to ſuch a ſinner, God may give wealth, but not give him a heart to uſe it: He gives the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous their deſire, but deals with them, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with the <hi>Iſraelites: he ſends leanneſſe with all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their ſouls,</hi> Pſal. 106. 15. 'Twas <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Divitias habent, quomodo habere dicimur fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brem, cum illa nos habeat:</hi> A Covetous man, hath Riches, as we are ſaid to have a Fever, when, we have not the Fever, but the Fever hath us: ſo the Covetous man, can not ſo much be ſaid, to <hi>have wealth,</hi> as wealth to <hi>have him,</hi> he doth not <hi>poſſeſſe,</hi> but is <hi>poſſeſſed:</hi> How many be there in the world, that live <hi>poor,</hi> for no other end, but to die <hi>rich?</hi> and almoſt ſtarve themſelves to <hi>day,</hi> out of an irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fear, that they may want to <hi>morrow? There is an evil</hi> (ſayes <hi>Solomon) which I have ſeen under the Sun, and it is common amongst men: A man to whom God hath given Riches, wealth, and honour, ſo that he wanteth nothing for his ſoul, of all that he poſſeſſeth, yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43794:12"/>
ſtranger eateth it: This is a vanity, and an evil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe,</hi> Eccleſ. 6. 1, 2. A Vanitie? and an Evil Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe? Nay, 'tis a <hi>Curſe,</hi> and a <hi>Curſe</hi> like that, which fell, on the incredulous Lord, that would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s prediction, of the plenty in <hi>Samaria,</hi> for behold, <hi>He ſeeth the plenty with his eyes, but he doth not eat thereof,</hi> 2 Kings 7. 2.</p>
            <p>Certainly, ſuch men, will never go to Hell, for <hi>Dives</hi> his ſin, for <hi>clothing themſelves with Purple, and fine Linen, and faring ſumptuouſly, every day,</hi> Luke 16. 19. No! their ſin is oppreſſion, and injuſtice, practiſed not more on <hi>other men,</hi> then, their <hi>own Perſons;</hi> Interdicting, and denying themſelves ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, defrauding, and <hi>robbing</hi> their <hi>mouthes,</hi> of what their <hi>hands</hi> have <hi>gotten:</hi> So, that while other ſinners, though they do not enjoy the happineſſe, and bliſſe of the other world, yet they are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly filled, with the contents, and pleaſures of this life: <hi>They eat, they drink, they enjoy the good of their labours, and it is their portion, as Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 18. One danceth, another drinkes away his life; one conſumes his dayes in exceſſe and Riot, another in chambering and wantonneſſe: Theſe, though they go down to Hell, the place of weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth, yet they go merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thither; But the Covetous man, is of all ſinners, moſt miſerable; He doth not enjoy himſelf, nor find comfort neither in <hi>this</hi> life, nor in <hi>that,</hi> which is to come: <hi>Dives,</hi> and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the rich Churl, is both, in one: <hi>Dives</hi> in his life time received his <hi>good things,</hi> but after death was tormented; <hi>Lazarus</hi> in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43794:12"/>
his life time received his <hi>evil things,</hi> but after death was comforted; but the covetous hath none of this variety, he partakes with <hi>both,</hi> only in the <hi>worſer part:</hi> In the midſt of all his plenty, he is like <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> in his <hi>life,</hi> poor, and wretched: and, for his plentie, thus abuſed, he is like <hi>Dives</hi> in his <hi>death,</hi> ſcorched in flames, and tormented: So, that look, with what ſolicitude, and carefulneſſe, other men get <hi>Heaven,</hi> with no leſſe, doth this man get <hi>Hell;</hi> Not only the kingdom of <hi>God,</hi> but the kingdom of <hi>Satan,</hi> ſuffers violence, and the violent take it by force: And as other men work out their <hi>Saluation,</hi> ſo this man works out his <hi>Damnation,</hi> with fear and trembling.</p>
            <p>But, becauſe, the Covetous may think it, not a <hi>Curſe,</hi> but a <hi>Bleſſing, to have wealth,</hi> though he have <hi>no heart to uſe it.</hi> Therefore <hi>Secondly,</hi> God doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes deprive him of his wealth, ſo that now he hath no wealth to uſe, that before, had no heart, to uſe that wealth, which he had: This ſin, leavens a mans whole ſubſtance, with Gods Curſe, which makes his <hi>baggs,</hi> like his <hi>deſires, bottomleſſe,</hi> or as it is in the Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> it is put into <hi>a bagge with holes,</hi> Hag. 1. 6. So that his Riches, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>make them wings, and flie away to heaven, Prov.</hi> 23. 5. before the owner deſcends to hell: <hi>He ſhall not ſave</hi> (ſaith Job) <hi>of that which he deſireth, there ſhall none of his wealth be left, therefore no man ſhall look for his goods,</hi> Job 20. 20, 21. That is, he ſhall die ſo poor, that no man ſhall care to be his <hi>heir,</hi> or <hi>executor:</hi> Nay, becauſe he <hi>truſted</hi> in his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43794:13"/>
Riches, and <hi>Sacrificed</hi> to his Net, applauded his own wit and induſtry, that got it; therefore, God ſhall deprive him of both, <hi>For he ſhall leave his riches in the midſt of his dayes, and at his later end he ſhall be a fool,</hi> Jer. 17. 11. So that his end ſhall be, <hi>begger,</hi> and <hi>fool,</hi> both in one: See a Pattern of Gods Juſtice in this kind, in his dealing with the <hi>Caldeans: Wo to him that increaſeth; that which is not his, how long? and to him that ladeth himſelf with thick clay: ſhall they not riſe up ſuddenly, that ſhall bite thee? and awake that ſhall vex thee? and thou ſhalt be for booties unto them, becauſe thou hast ſpoiled many nations, all the remnant of the nations ſhall ſpoil thee,</hi> Hab. 2. 6, 7, &amp;c. Firſt, or laſt, God will ſpoil the ſpoilers, either by his ſecret curſe, <hi>blaſting,</hi> or <hi>blowing</hi> upon their eſtate, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 9. or by the hand, of a greater oppreſſor; ſo that <hi>he,</hi> that hath been <hi>Praedo minoris,</hi> ſhall (as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks) become, <hi>Praeda majoris.</hi> He that hath preyed upon the <hi>leſſe,</hi> ſhall himſelf become a prey to the <hi>greater:</hi> 'Tis juſt with God to do ſo: <hi>Thou ſhalt be for booties to them.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43794:13"/>
            <head>The Second SERMON.</head>
            <p>AS God, doth puniſh the Covetous, in his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> ſo, Secondly, he doth puniſh him in his <hi>Children;</hi> and in <hi>them,</hi> fruſtrates the end, and intentions, of all the <hi>fathers</hi> hoarding up: what makes the Covetous, thus to inlarge his deſires as Hell, to ſnatch on the right hand, and on the left, to lade himſelf with thick clay? why! tis to raiſe a houſe, to advance a family; but how often doth <hi>Prodigality,</hi> become heir to <hi>Covetouſneſſe?</hi> The <hi>Love of Money,</hi> though it may bring, good <hi>materials,</hi> to build a Houſe, yet, it ſeldom, or never, laies <hi>a ſure Foundation:</hi> No! <hi>Job</hi> tels us right, <hi>Aedificat ut Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea domum ſuam, He builds his houſe, as a Moth, and as a Booth, that the keeper maketh,</hi> Job 27. 18. Builds his houſe as a Moth? and, as a Booth, that the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er maketh? how is that? How doth the <hi>Moth,</hi> build his <hi>houſe?</hi> or the <hi>Keeper</hi> his <hi>Booth?</hi> The <hi>Moth, devours</hi> the houſe he <hi>builds,</hi> and <hi>then</hi> devours it, even <hi>when</hi> he builds it: The <hi>Keeper,</hi> builds but <hi>ſightly,</hi> becauſe he doth not intend it for <hi>perpetuity:</hi> Booths, you know, in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> were <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems</hi> of a <hi>Tranſitory, unſetled condition:</hi> here to <hi>day,</hi> and gone to <hi>morrow;</hi> and yet, <hi>aedificat, ſicut Tinea, &amp;c.</hi> The Oppreſſour, and the Covetous,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43794:14"/>
(for it is he, of whom <hi>Job</hi> there ſpeaks) <hi>builds his houſe as a Moth, and as a Booth that the Keeper ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have a <hi>Proverb,</hi> and it is an <hi>Irreligious</hi> one, <hi>'Tis happy for the Child, whoſe Father goes to the Devil:</hi> you know the meaning of it: But, as God ſaid of that <hi>Proverb, The Fathers have eaten ſowre grapes, and the Childrens teeth are ſet an edge: As I live ſaith the Lord God, ye ſhall not have occaſion any more to uſe this Proverb in Iſrael,</hi> Ezek. 18. 3. So, let me ſay, of this <hi>Proverb,</hi> as I live ſaith the Lord, as ye never <hi>had,</hi> ſo ye never <hi>ſhall</hi> have occaſion, to uſe this Proverb in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for, God, ſhall <hi>take away the father with hooks, and his poſterity with fiſh-hooks, and they ſhall go out at the breaches,</hi> Amos 4. 2, 3. Let them build <hi>houſes,</hi> and <hi>families,</hi> as ſtrong, as they can, and (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>Leave the reſt of their ſubſtance</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 17. 24.</note> 
               <hi>for their babes;</hi> yet the <hi>Curſe</hi> of God, like the <hi>whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind from the wilderneſſe,</hi> Job 1. 19. ſhall <hi>ſmite the houſe,</hi> aye, ſo <hi>ſmite it,</hi> that <hi>their Poſterity ſhall go out at the breaches: Nay, their children,</hi> (as <hi>Zophar</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>ſhall flatter the poor,</hi> Job 20. 10. They ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to that extream <hi>beggery,</hi> and <hi>want,</hi> that they ſhall flatter a mean man, for an alms, and fawne up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a poor man, for a cruſt of bread.</p>
            <p>If therefore thou doſt think to raiſe a houſe, or advance a family, lay not the foundation, in this ſin, <hi>This Love of Money;</hi> This were to <hi>build,</hi> but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>ſand,</hi> and inſtead of conſulting <hi>honour</hi> to thy poſteritie, thou wilt as the Prophet ſpeaks, but <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult ſhame to thy houſe, and ſin againſt thine own ſoul,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43794:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Hab.</hi> 2. 10. But if thou wilt lay a ſure foundation, whereon to raiſe a Family, if thou wilt leave thy poſteritie, a <hi>ſecure,</hi> and <hi>durable</hi> eſtate, follow theſe directions, <hi>Purchaſe</hi> for them, by thine <hi>Alms,</hi> and <hi>Charitable works,</hi> the Prayers of the poor, and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: <hi>Give Alms of all that ye poſſeſse, and behold all things are clean unto you,</hi> Luke 11. 41. <hi>Revive,</hi> that antiquated, loſt piece of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which our forefathers called <hi>Charity,</hi> but this preſent fanatical, Atheiſtical age, hath diſgraced, with the name of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Merits:</hi> follow <hi>Daniels</hi> counſel to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Break off thy ſins by righteouſneſſe, and thine iniquities, by ſhewing mercy to the poor,</hi> Dan. 4. 27. It may not only be a lengthning to thine <hi>own</hi> tranquillitie, but it may prove a <hi>reſerve;</hi> a Treaſure laid up in heaven for thy <hi>Poſterity,</hi> theſe works may prove importunate Advocates with God for <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>thine,</hi> after thee: <hi>Settle upon them,</hi> the durable <hi>Patrimony</hi> of a Religious, ſober, and honeſt <hi>Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Bequeath</hi> them, the <hi>legacy</hi> of thine own good <hi>Example,</hi> in all vertuous, and godly converſation: And then, though the portion of <hi>Earthly riches,</hi> which thou leaveſt them, be but <hi>little,</hi> yet, it is a great deal better, to leave them a <hi>little, well gotten,</hi> with <hi>Gods bleſſing,</hi> then a <hi>great deal, ill gotten,</hi> with <hi>Gods curſe,</hi> mingled amongſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> as God puniſh the Covetous in his <hi>eſtate,</hi> and in his <hi>children,</hi> ſo he doth puniſh him eſpecially in his <hi>own Perſon;</hi> and that, as <hi>Caietan</hi> obſerves, Firſt, in his <hi>body,</hi> Secondly, in his <hi>ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> this ſin, leads the ſinner headlong to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43794:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and <hi>perdition,</hi> before at the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe: And the ſinner <hi>pierceth himſelf thorow with many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows;</hi> at the later end of this verſe: <hi>Nec cibus ſecurus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Donat. Ep. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſomnuſve contingit,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian) ſuſpirat in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivio, vigilat in pluma:</hi> He neither <hi>eats,</hi> nor <hi>ſleeps</hi> in <hi>ſecurity,</hi> he <hi>ſighs</hi> at a <hi>feaſt,</hi> nor do the temples of his head take any reſt, though on his <hi>down-bed: for the abundance of the rich, will not ſuffer him to ſleep, Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 22. And the wiſe ſon of <hi>Sirach</hi> tels us, <hi>That watching for riches doth conſume the fleſh, and the care thereof, driveth away ſleep,</hi> Eccleſ. 31. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> if none of theſe Puniſhments light upon this ſin; yet in this, the ſinner, <hi>ſins againſt his own ſoul,</hi> Hab. 2. 10. And that <hi>Firſt,</hi> by <hi>ſealing</hi> it up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>impenitency,</hi> here; and <hi>Secondly,</hi> by <hi>ſealing</hi> it up, under <hi>eternal torments</hi> hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> this ſin, <hi>ſeals</hi> up the ſoul of the ſinner, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>impenitency</hi> here; for <hi>this</hi> ſin, like <hi>that</hi> of <hi>luſt,</hi> ſeldom finds the grace of Repentance; I will not ſay, that God, <hi>will not</hi> give him the <hi>grace</hi> of Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but if he do, I may boldly ſay, <hi>There's a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 19. 24.</note> 
               <hi>gone through the eye of an Needle:</hi> for in <hi>this,</hi> it is a ſtate more dangerous, leſſe recoverable, then <hi>luſt:</hi> for while <hi>age,</hi> oftentimes, proves a remedy to this, and other ſins, which grow old, and decrepid with the body of the ſinner, This <hi>Love of Money,</hi> of all others, is <hi>Peccatum Senectutis,</hi> the <hi>Sin of old age,</hi> and is <hi>then ſtrongeſt,</hi> when the ſinner, is <hi>weakeſt,</hi> and in a prepoſterous manner of ſinning, makes proviſion for the <hi>Viaticum</hi> of his life, in the very <hi>concluſion</hi> of it, as if he had ſet out, but <hi>yeſterday:</hi> and therefore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43794:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Ghetius de Coma,</hi> in his caſes of Conſcience, thinks it<note place="margin">Lib. 1. verbo, Avaritia.</note> is not impertinent, to move the queſtion, <hi>whether the Natural proneneſſe, that is in old men, to the ſin of Covetouſneſſe, doth excuſe them from the guilt?</hi> but he reſolves it in the Negative: And the Reaſon, why this ſin, cleaves ſo faſt to old age, when other ſins languiſh, and fall off; is, Becauſe, the <hi>ſoul,</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet upon <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> which alone, can ſatisfie that better part of man, and other luſts which did uſe to entertain, and court the ſoul, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing with age, it finds the luſt of Coveting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, the fitteſt ſin, wherein to exerciſe it ſelf: So <hi>Simonides,</hi> in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> being upbraided, for being Covetous, made it his Apology; That whereas, the delight of other pleaſures, was gone, he did foment, and nouriſh, his old age with that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>Profitable pleaſure:</hi> Hence it is, that many, having eſcaped the danger of the <hi>high-way ground,</hi> having underſtood, the word of God preached, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the ſame; And the danger of the <hi>ſtony gound,</hi> in undergoing ſome troubles, and perſecutions, for the Truth, yet nouriſhing in themſelves, too great a love, of worldly riches, they have ſhipwracked at this Rock, ſtifled all their graces, choaked all their hopeful beginnings, <hi>with the cares of the world, and the deceitfulneſſe of Riches,</hi> as our Saviour ſpeaks, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> as he ſins againſt his own ſoul, by <hi>ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> it up under <hi>Impenitency,</hi> here, ſo he ſins againſt his own ſoul, by <hi>ſealing</hi> it up, under <hi>eternal torments,</hi> hereafter: <hi>What is the hope of the Hypocrite, though
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43794:16"/>
he have gained,</hi> (ſaith Job) <hi>when God takes away his ſoul?</hi> Job 27. 8. Certainly whatſoever he <hi>gaineth,</hi> he <hi>loſeth heaven,</hi> the thought whereof (without doubt) is the greateſt torment in <hi>Hell. The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous hath no inheritance in the kingdom of Chriſt, and of God,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) Epheſ. 5. 5. and again, <hi>The Covetous ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 9. If therefore, there be any which hear me this day, who are not reſolved upon the queſtion, which is beſt, to ſave your <hi>ſouls,</hi> or your <hi>eſtates,</hi> conſider that of our Saviour, and let it ſink down into your hearts, <hi>What is a man profited, if he ſhall gain the whole world, and loſe his own ſoul?</hi> Mat. 16. 16. A Text, moſt ſeaſonable for theſe times of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to be admitted, into your <hi>bed-chambers,</hi> and <hi>cloſets,</hi> and <hi>counting houſes,</hi> into your moſt retired, inmoſt <hi>thoughts,</hi> when ye deliberate what to do, or reſolve on, in theſe times of danger, and diſtraction; For as this is <hi>Hora Tentationis,</hi> ſo this is <hi>Tentatio Horae;</hi> as this is the <hi>time</hi> of <hi>Temptation,</hi> ſo this is the <hi>Temptation</hi> of the <hi>Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, as well as I could, I have made good, this <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> poſition, That, <hi>The love of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is the Root of all Evil,</hi> both of the <hi>evil of guilt,</hi> and, the <hi>evil of puniſhment:</hi> I ſhall now, in the laſt place, by way of Application, only offer you, ſome <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> or Conſiderations to <hi>dehort,</hi> and ſome <hi>helps</hi> to <hi>preſerve</hi> you, from ſo dangerous a ſin.</p>
            <p>And here <hi>Firſt,</hi> that the Impetuouſneſſe of this<note place="margin">Part. 3.</note> Paſſion may not violently tranſport thee, ſtay a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and conſider thy <hi>Saviours Poverty: Magna abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43794:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
&amp; nimis magna, quod dives fieri velit vermicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, pro quo, Deus majeſtatis, pauper eſſe voluit,</hi> ſaith S. Bernard: <hi>It is a foul abuſe, and an abuſe not to be indured, That, that worm ſhould covet to be made rich, for whoſe ſake, the Lord of glory, was content, to be made poor:</hi> He that laid the foundations of the <hi>earth,</hi> and ſpread out the <hi>heavens</hi> like a curtain over it, <hi>had not a place, where to lay his head:</hi> He that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured<note place="margin">Mat. 8. 20.</note> up the <hi>mines</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> in the deep <hi>vaults,</hi> and <hi>bowels</hi> of the earth, was fain to <hi>Angle for</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſilver</hi> to pay his <hi>Tribute:</hi> doth thy courſe garment trouble thee? Remember his <hi>ſwadling clothes:</hi> Is thy bead uneaſie? yet it is not harder then his <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:</hi> Is thy houſe poor, and mean? forget not, that he had not a houſe where to lay his head: If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God gives thee <hi>Poverty,</hi> he deals no worſe with <hi>thee,</hi> then with his own <hi>Son:</hi> But for the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of a good Conſcience, haſt thou loſt All? thou art bound to rejoyce, and to glorifie God, in that behalf, that he hath vouchſafed thee the honour, and counted thee worthy, to ſuffer for his <hi>Truth:</hi> whatſoever fleſh, and bloud may mutter, 'tis a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galio,</hi> a favour, not vouchſafed to every one: but yet, withall remember, that <hi>loſſe of goods,</hi> is but the <hi>leaſt,</hi> and the <hi>loweſt</hi> of the ſufferings of the Saints: if God call us to <hi>Martyrdome,</hi> to reſiſtance unto bloud, and to the laying down of our lives, for the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his Truth, the Juſtice of our cauſe will be <hi>Infularum Loco,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks, the <hi>Garland, and Ribonds, to the Sacrifice;</hi> Theſe, are but the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>after ſufferings of Chriſt, which we his members are to fill up in our fleſh,</hi> Col. 1. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43794:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider that in deſiring <hi>Riches,</hi> thou doſt deſire things, that are <hi>extreamly dangerous;</hi> and contain in them, a <hi>poſſibility,</hi> whereby the <hi>owner</hi> may be made <hi>extreamly miſerable:</hi> for, beſides, that they are a condition, wherein, fortune hath a greater ſcope, and latitude, wherin to inflict croſſes, ſo that often times, they prove a ſnare, and expoſe their owner to envy, and oppreſſion, (for we live in thoſe times, in which <hi>Poverty,</hi> is a protection, more ſecure then <hi>Innocency,</hi> a <hi>ſanctuary,</hi> if not more <hi>ſacred,</hi> yet more <hi>Inviolable</hi>) So on the other ſide, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that <hi>riches,</hi> and plenty, have temptations, far greater, then <hi>poverty:</hi> It was the Obſervation of a <hi>Religious Votary,</hi> That the Devils of <hi>Conſolation,</hi> as he cals them, are more dangerous, then thoſe of <hi>Tribulation:</hi> certainly, of the Two extreams, the wiſe man, in that prayer, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. plainly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, that the Temptations of <hi>riches,</hi> are more <hi>dangerous,</hi> then thoſe, of <hi>poverty: Give me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>neither poverty, nor riches, feed me with food con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for me, leſt I be full, and deny thee, and ſay, who is the Lord? or leſt, I be poor, and ſteal, and take the name of my God in vain.</hi> Verſe 8, 9. <hi>Poverty,</hi> may drive a man to <hi>ſteal,</hi> to deal unjuſtly, and then to forſwear it, <hi>and take the name of God in vain:</hi> but if a man be <hi>rich,</hi> and <hi>full,</hi> he is in danger, to <hi>deny God,</hi> and in pride of heart to ſay, with <hi>Pharaoh, who is the Lord?</hi> Certainly, it is very difficult, to be <hi>rich,</hi> and not to neglect God, and to <hi>truſt in riches?</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this very ground, our Saviour ſayes, <hi>That, it is eaſier for a Camel, to go thorow the eye of a needle,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43794:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> Mat. 19. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider, in what manner, thou cameſt <hi>into</hi> the world, and how thou ſhalt go <hi>out,</hi> we were <hi>born, Sine Integumento,</hi> and we <hi>depart, Sine viatico,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. 44.</note> as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaks: Nature, doth furniſh us, with proviſion, neither, at our coming <hi>into</hi> the world, nor at our going <hi>out:</hi> of all that which thou doſt poſſeſſe, what ſhalt thou carry with thee, but a <hi>Winding-ſheet,</hi> and a <hi>Coffin?</hi> perhaps neither: What a madneſſe is it then, to wound thy ſoul, to get, what ſhortly thou muſt leave behind thee, and carry with thee, nothing elſe, but the guilt, of ill gotten wealth? Perhaps thou wilt anſwer, Though, I leave my wealth, yet I ſhall leave it to my <hi>Child,</hi> that ſhall be after me: Though, this cannot be eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Covetous mans <hi>Apologie, For there is one alone</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>and there is not a Second; yea, he hath neither child, nor brother, yet is there no end of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, neither is his eye ſatisfied with riches, neither ſaith he, for whom do I labour, and bereave my ſoul of good?</hi> Eccleſ. 4. 8. But ſuppoſe, thou haſt <hi>children,</hi> and canſt ſay, though, I leave my wealth, yet I ſhall leave it to my Child that ſhall be after me: yet let me tell thee, thou knoweſt not, whether that Child, will be a <hi>wiſe man,</hi> or a <hi>fool:</hi> This, <hi>Solomon</hi> cals <hi>vanity,</hi> and for <hi>this,</hi> very <hi>reaſon,</hi> he did even <hi>hate his labour,</hi> as himſelf ſpeaketh: <hi>I hated all my labour, which I had taken under the Sun, becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſhould leave it to a man that ſhall be after me, and who knows, whether he ſhall be a wiſe man or a fool, yet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43794:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he ſhall have rule over all my labours, wherein I have laboured, and wherein, I have ſhewed my ſelf wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun, this alſo is vanity,</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 19. Thy wealth, may prove to thy <hi>poſterity,</hi> but an <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to ſerve ſome <hi>luſt,</hi> to <hi>commit,</hi> ſome <hi>ſin:</hi> an Inſtrument of <hi>Gods diſhonour,</hi> and their own <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> Nay, as thy wealth, was <hi>uſeleſſe</hi> to thy <hi>ſelf,</hi> ſo may thy <hi>Children,</hi> be <hi>uſeleſs</hi> to <hi>themſelves, uſeleſs</hi> to the <hi>publick,</hi> to their <hi>Country,</hi> uſeleſſe to the <hi>Church of Chriſt:</hi> They may be <hi>fools,</hi> or <hi>prodigals,</hi> or <hi>extreamly wicked,</hi> the very Curſe, and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their fathers <hi>Avarice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Conſider, that when by ſordid, and diſhoneſt courſes, thou haſt got a great eſtate, yet this great eſtate doth not <hi>fill</hi> thy <hi>Appetite: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idem ſunt termini Regni tui Alexander &amp; mundi,</hi> as he ſpake in the <hi>Suaſory:</hi> The ſame bounds, meaſured <hi>Alexanders Empire,</hi> and the <hi>world,</hi> and yet, <hi>inventus eſt, qui concupiſceret aliquid poſt omnia:</hi> he would have more then <hi>all;</hi> in coveting a <hi>Second</hi> world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was full maſter of the <hi>Firſt: Habes A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum, habes argentum, concupiſcis aurum, &amp; concupiſcis Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentum, habes, &amp; concupiſcis, Plenus es &amp; ſitis, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eſt, non Opulentia,</hi> ſayes S. <hi>Auſtin: Thou haſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ser. 3. de verb. Apoſt.</note> 
               <hi>gold, and thou haſt ſilver, and yet thou doſt covet gold and covet ſilver; Thou haſt, and yet doſt covet; Thou art full, but not ſatisfied; this is not a fulneſſe but a diſeaſe:</hi> for <hi>Riches,</hi> were no more made, to fill the <hi>ſoul,</hi> then <hi>Learning,</hi> or <hi>Knowledge</hi> were to fill a <hi>bag:</hi> He that (as one ſpeaks) ſhall ſhoot an Arrow, cut of a Plough, or hunt a Hare with an Elephant, cannot
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43794:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
be ſaid to be <hi>unfortunate,</hi> for miſſing the prey, but <hi>fooliſh,</hi> in chuſing ſuch improper Inſtruments, to obtain it: ſo, he that ſhall ſeek for <hi>content</hi> in <hi>Riches,</hi> or the things of this life, is not ſo <hi>unhappy,</hi> in loſing his deſires, as <hi>vaine,</hi> and <hi>fooliſh,</hi> in the choice of ſuch means, to obtain them. And therefore, it was not without <hi>myſterie,</hi> obſerved, amongſt the Ancients, That they, who made Gods of gold, and ſilver, of hope, and fear, peace, and war, Garlick, and Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; beaſts, and ſerpents: nay, though they deiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, diſeaſes, <hi>&amp; quod dicere nolo:</hi> what, without breach of modeſty I cannot name, yet, <hi>Funeſta Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunia, templo, nondum habitas,</hi> They never deified <hi>money,</hi> nor erected any Temple to it: thereby meaning, that, though wealth was admired by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or abuſed underſtandings, yet, from <hi>riches,</hi> (further then they ſerved, and ſupplied the exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and neceſſities of nature) nothing conducing, to mans reall content, and happineſſe, could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
            <p>While therefore, theſe <hi>conſiderations,</hi> convince your <hi>judgements:</hi> let theſe <hi>means,</hi> and <hi>helps</hi> aſſiſt your <hi>wils,</hi> in the great work of mortifying, this powerful luſt, The <hi>Love of Money, which is the Root of all Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Labour, to anchor thy ſoul, with content, to ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I have learned, in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver eſtute I am, therewith to be content,</hi> Phil. 4. 11. for <hi>content,</hi> is a nearer cut, to wealth, then <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs:</hi> For, what matters it, whether thou be rich <hi>Tuo, &amp; pationti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, beneficio, an fortun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>?</hi> as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43794:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks, by the benefit of thine own, <hi>modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. 119.</note> and <hi>contentation,</hi> or the <hi>bounty</hi> of fortune? for as he reaſons on, <hi>Nihil intereſt utrum non deſideres, an habeas?</hi> where is the difference, between having, and not deſiring? There is content in both: for, as our <hi>life,</hi> doth not conſiſt, in the abundance of the things which a man poſſeſſeth, ſo neither doth his <hi>content:</hi> there is a way, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> found out, of <hi>having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 10. Content, reconciles this ſeeming contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things:</hi> for, as he, that is maſter of a <hi>great eſtate,</hi> is ſtill <hi>poor,</hi> if he think it to be <hi>too little:</hi> So he that is poſſeſſed of a <hi>mean eſtate,</hi> is <hi>rich,</hi> if he think it to be <hi>enough:</hi> He that ſeeks for Content, without <hi>himſelf,</hi> loſeth both <hi>himſelf,</hi> and <hi>it: Quareigitur à Fortuna, potius impetrem, ut det, quàm à me, ne petam?</hi> ſayes the ſame <hi>Seneca, why ſhould Irather deſire of God, to give me wealth, then to deſire of my ſelf, not to deſire it?</hi> I conclude this, with the Epigrammatiſt, <hi>Fis fieri di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, Pontice? nil cupias:</hi> He is abundantly rich, that deſires nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Learn to <hi>compare,</hi> things <hi>Temporal,</hi> with things <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and ſee, how the ſcales will turne: <hi>Vileſcunt temporalia, cum conſiderantur aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Gregory:</hi> the <hi>Glo-worm,</hi> may ſeem, <hi>a glorious light,</hi> till the <hi>Sun,</hi> that <hi>eye of the world,</hi> be diſcloſed, and <hi>Temporal riches</hi> may ſeem, a <hi>great bleſſing,</hi> until they be weighed, with the <hi>Eternal,</hi> in the <hi>ballance of the Sanctuary;</hi> Raiſe thy meditations therefore, to the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> walk about
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43794:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
her wals, mark all her bul warks, tell all her towers, and in compariſon of that <hi>City that is above,</hi> thou wilt ſay, of all <hi>Earthly poſſeſſions,</hi> as <hi>Hyram</hi> did, of the Cities which <hi>Solomon</hi> gave him, <hi>they pleaſed him not, and he called them the land of Cabul unto this day; that is the dirty land,</hi> 1 Kings 9. 13. What were the pleaſures and riches of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the pomp, and glory of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court in the eyes of <hi>Moſes</hi> after he had once ſeen his God? what was the world, and the vanities thereof, in S. <hi>Peters</hi> thoughts, after he had a <hi>glimpſe</hi> of the glory of heaven, &amp; a <hi>ray</hi> of the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe thereof, in the <hi>Transfiguration of Chriſt?</hi> As ſome <hi>great Peer</hi> therefore, that hath been uſed to <hi>ſtately ſhews, &amp; courtly magnificence,</hi> doth not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe ſo much, as to caſt an eye, or a glance, towards the mean, and worthleſſe <hi>Gewgaws of a Pedlars pack,</hi> which yet ſilly <hi>children,</hi> and <hi>fools</hi> behold with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and greedineſſe, their eyes dwelling long upon them; So, the <hi>ſoul,</hi> that by divine <hi>contemplation,</hi> hath its <hi>converſation in heaven,</hi> ſcorns to ſuffer its ſelf to be tranſported, with the <hi>traſh,</hi> and <hi>toyes,</hi> of this vain, and tranſitory world: I have read of a Spiritual perſon, who ſaw heaven but in a dream. dream, but 'twas ſuch a dream, as made deep impreſſions in him: the glory, and happineſſe of it, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, with vigorous, and pertinacious phantaſms, not eaſily diſbanding: So, that when he awaked, he knew not his own Cell: he remembred not him, that ſlept, in the ſame <hi>Dorter,</hi> with him; nor could he tell, how <hi>night,</hi> and <hi>day,</hi> were diſtinguiſhed nor could he diſcern, <hi>oyl,</hi> from <hi>mine,</hi> but, paſſionately
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43794:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cried out for his viſion again, <hi>Redde mihi campos meos floridos, Colnmnam auream, Comitem Hierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, aſſiſtentes Angelos: Give me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fields again, my moſt delicious fields: Give me my Pillar of a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Light; my Companion S.</hi> Jerom, <hi>and my aſſiſtant Angels:</hi> And this laſted, until he was told of his duty, when the fear of a ſin diſincharmed him, and cauſed him to take care, leſt he loſt the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> out of a tranſported greedineſſe, to poſſeſſe the <hi>ſhadow:</hi> the ſame operation (at leaſt in ſome proportion) which that <hi>viſion,</hi> had on him, may <hi>meditation</hi> have on thee: Labour therefore, to get a piercing eye, in meditation, to ſee the Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, ſend out thy ſoul, in a devout <hi>extaſie,</hi> contemplate, the glory, and beauty of heaven, weigh the happineſſe of the Saints, and Angels, and of the <hi>Spirits of juſt men made perfect:</hi> Think upon thoſe raviſhing, unſpeakable Conſolations, that like a torrent of joy, ſhall ſwallowup thoſe, that are redeemed from the earth; And theſe meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, muſt needs kindle, and inflame thy affections, inſeparably to be united to God, and work in thee an holy impatience of delay, and a ſtaying here, a loathing of the things, of this world, and a weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe, of the prolongation of thy pilgrimage here in this world, being wholly bent, upon that, which is to come; ſaying with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, My ſoul is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>inſt for God, even for the living God, when ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to appear before the preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce of God,</hi> Pſalm 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all this inordinate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:43794:20"/>
proceeds from diſtruſt, and diffidence of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and providence, providing for our ſelves, becauſe we do not believe, that God, will provide for us; <hi>have faith in God,</hi> knowing, that he hath ſaid, <hi>I will never leave thee, nor for ſake thee,</hi> Heb. 13. 5. Certainly our <hi>great cares,</hi> come from our, <hi>little faith.</hi> great <hi>faith</hi> would leſſen our <hi>cares;</hi> for <hi>Faith,</hi> doth not only <hi>purifie,</hi> but <hi>ſatisfie,</hi> the heart: So, that whereas before, <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> did make <hi>Gold,</hi> thy <hi>God,</hi> now quite contrary, this <hi>affiance,</hi> ſhall make <hi>God,</hi> thy <hi>Gold:</hi> for as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>if thou return to the Almighty, thou ſhalt then lay up gold, as duſt, and the gold of Ophir as the ſtones of the brook; Erit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotens, Lectiſſimum aurum tuum,</hi> as <hi>Junius</hi> reads that place: <hi>And the Almighty ſhall be thy choice gold, and ſilver, and ſtrength unto thee,</hi> Job 22. 23, 24, &amp;<hi>c.</hi> So, <hi>undervaluing</hi> the <hi>world,</hi> the wealth, &amp; glory, and pomp of it, thou wilt <hi>prefer God,</hi> in all thy deſires, ſaying with the <hi>Pſalmiſt, The Lord himſelf is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine inheritance, and of my cup; Thou ſhalt maintain my lot; The lot is fallen unto me, in a fair ground, yea, I have a goodly heritage,</hi> Pſal. 16. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To all theſe <hi>conſiderations,</hi> and <hi>means,</hi> to <hi>prevent,</hi> or <hi>caſt out</hi> this <hi>Love of Money which is the Root of all Evil:</hi> joyn, fervent prayer to God, that he would make theſe <hi>means,</hi> and thy <hi>endeavours,</hi> effectual unto thee: Pray with the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> in the place but now, alleadged, <hi>Incline my heart O Lord unto thy Teſtimonies, and not unto Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> and he, that <hi>knowing the plague of his own
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43794:21"/>
heart,</hi> ſhall thus pray againſt it, <hi>Then hear thou in heaven, O Lord, thy dwelling place, and do, according to all that thy ſervant calleth unto thee for, even for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, to whom with thee, O Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed, all honour, and praiſe, dominion, and power, now and for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43794:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
